Mino marbles from Fiesole
The 4 marbles outlined here were made by Mino da Fiesole between 1461 and 1463 for the altar of St. Jerome within the basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore. They were commissioned by the Cardinal of Cardinal Guillame D'Estouteville and represent scenes from the life of St. Jerome.
The first slab is two-sided: above is represented San Girolamo penitent in the desert on his knees while beating a chest on his chest, while below is the saint depicted in his study he is engaged in the translation of sacred texts.
In the second and third marble there is a very famous legend: San Girolamo lifts from the paw of a lion a thorn, who returns gratefully and returns to the saint the escaped cattle. In this slab the book is closed to indicate the acquisition of knowledge and the completion of the work.
At the end of the work there is the fourth marble in which the death of the saint is depicted through the appearance of St. Augustine, in which Saint Jerome is located in an almond and is presented by St. John the Baptist.
Lapidarium
Lapidarium literally signs "that contains marbles": in fact, in this section of the museum are collected sarcophagi tombstones marbles and tombstones.
The lapidarium is located in the upper loggia of the viridarium, the secret garden building that was moved from the center of Piazza Venezia to the other side of the Venice Palace (in the current Piazza San Marco) to give greater visibility to the Upper House of the Fatherland. From the excavations carried out during this shift, many classic and medieval marbles come from.
Inside the collection there are marble of Roman origin from the 2nd and 3rd century from urban excavations, marble and tombstones from the medieval times of the 9th and 10th century and finally finds of Renaissance age.
Iulia Iusta funerary funeral
This spell was used in the Roman era to indicate the place of a burial, in detail it is dedicated to a woman of a certain social thickness since the Latin inscription below is said to be the wife of a Roman official who was dealing with finances in provinces of Africa.
To tell us the period in which this woman is lived is the particular hairstyle of the Adrian age, this is because it was a costume for Roman women to dress their hair like royal family women.
On the sides of the wing are placed a saucer on the left and a jug on the right, instruments used during sacramental rituals in honor of the deceased.
Sarcophagus with Nike myth by Ganimede
The front of this sarcophagus is centered on the young deceased supported by two Nike, two winged wins, below (below the round) the myth of Ganimede, a young shepherd whose Zeus fell in love and for this reason raped him and made him godfather of the gods ,. On the sides you can see 4 puttins representing the 4 seasons
Winter remains only a wing while autumn has in hand the game, summer a basket of fruit and spring a bunch of flowers. Both the bastards and the myth express the idea of ​​immortality and cyclicity of time.
In the lower left is depicted Ocean as it fights with a sea monster.