Palazzo Venezia
In 1455, Venetian Cardinal Pietro Barbo started building his residence, which was placed close to the Church of San Marco, which had been named by his uncle Pope Eugenio IV Condulmer.
The story of the palace is divided into two phases: during the first part was built the whole corner from the large corner tower (which incorporates and replaces a pre-existing tower dates back to the XIII-XIV century, known as Torre della Biscia) at the entrance of Piazza Venezia ; in this area is located the Cardinal Barbo's (developed on two floors) flat, indicated by the coat of arms of the lion rampant with the cardinal hat.
The second phase begins when Cardinal Pietro Barbo was elected Pope by the name of Paul II (1464): instead of leaving the building, the pontiff decided to expand it by building the part that from Piazza Venezia goes towards the path of the Plebiscite, thus adjusting it to the role of apostolic palace. At the same time, the viridarium was built, a "secret" garden where the Pope could enjoy his free time without having to leave the palace.
Not yet satisfied, in 1468 Pope Paul II extended his residence further by introducing an interior courtyard to the center of the palace and an elegant porch that remained unfinished. In addition, during the same period, the building of the interior of the building was completed with the construction of the corner side between Piazza Venezia and Via del Plebiscito.
In 1471, Pope Paul II died and leaves the palace in his grandson, Cardinal Marco Barbo. Following the death of Cardinal Lorenzo Things, he finished building the last halls on the façade of Via del Plebiscito, including the Sala Regia and the Sala del Mappamondo.
The building remained a papal site until 1564, when it was handed over by Pope Pius IV to the Republic of Venice as a residence for its ambassadors who will live there "in condominium" with the cardinals holding the San Marco Basilica (also Venetians).
The seventeenth century was a period of decay in which the building lost importance; the interests of the palace resumed in 1714, the year when the famous balcony was added to the central window of the facade on Piazza Venezia. Following the Treaty of Campoformio in 1797, Palazzo Venezia was sold to the Austro-Hungarian empire, which assigned it to its ambassadors. In 1909 - 1910 the viridarium (called "Palazzetto") was demolished and moved to its current location in order to expand Piazza Venezia and to make the Altar of Patria visible to those who came from Via del Corso.
The palace remained in Austria until 1916, when it was claimed by the Italian government.