This great wooden crucifix was designed to decorate an altar of the church of Santa Maria in Aracoeli. The body of Christ is depicted as "Christus patiens" (ie "suffering") between the Virgin and Saint John the Evangelist. Traces of original colors are found in the legs, in the thong and in the hands of Christ and were recovered during a restoration carried out in the 1960s. The work is an interesting testimony of the Roman pictorial production of the 13th century.