The Altoviti Hall takes its name from the frescoes that are there, once placed in Palazzo Altoviti.
The palace was built for the Florentine banker Bindo Altoviti and was facing Castel Sant'Angelo, between Piazza del Ponte and the Tiber (area where Tuscan bankers lived at that time). In 1553 Bindo Altoviti commissioned Giorgio Vasari to freshen the palace loggia. In 1887 the frescoes were separated from the wall by the technique of tearing from Pietro Cecconi and reassembled on canvases in Palazzo Corsini to Lungara. The following year, with the promulgation of the "Tiber Law" (1876), which included the construction of muraglions along the river to prevent frequent flooding, Altoviti palace was destroyed.
The Vasarian frescoes came to Venice Palace in 1917 by decision of Hermanin and were reconstituted according to their original arrangement. The time was contextualized by the painter Rupelli, who adorned the walls with grotesque grottoes in Renaissance style.
At the center of the vault there is a large oval depicting the tribute to Ceres.
To the right of the oval we find Ceres (goddess of abundance and agriculture) sitting on a throne with cornucopia and corn ears. To the right of the throne there is a snake, a symbol of the rebirth of the Earth (this animal has in fact the characteristic to change the skin every year). There are also 11 characters, saints and priests who give homage to the goddess. Among the priests there is the commander himself of the fresco, Bindo Altoviti covered with a golden mantle and behind him Michelangelo Buonarroti wrapped in a purple dress; Michelangelo was in good standing with the banker, as both were part of the republican and anti-metic faction together with Vasari and Pope Julius III (funded by Bindo Altoviti).
On the sides of the oval there are two panels with two senile figures crowned by two girls: the one on the left represents the river of Florence, the Arno, identifiable by the presence of the lion Marzocco and the lily (bottom right). The panel on the right, on the other hand, symbolizes the coronation of the Tiber river, accompanied by the lizard with Romulus and Remo (bottom left).
Along the perimeter of the hall are represented the 12 months of the year within ovals and hexagons. The first month of the year, according to the order in which they are arranged, is March as according to the Tuscans on March 25 (the day of the announcement) was the first of the year. On the side overlooking Via degli Astalli, the frescoes representing March and April are based on subjects of classical art.
On the left we have Mars, with Mars, who in the Roman world resumed the resumption of war activities, suspended during the winter. In the face of the god we recognize the portrait of Giambattista Altoviti (the firstborn of Bindo) who was promised as a bride Clarice Ridolfi, who is portrayed in the hex of April, having the body of Venus. The tribute Bindo Altoviti offers to Cerere symbolically aims to promote the continuity of his lineage through the marriage of his son, wishing the young couple prosperity and fertility.
The other 10 ovals and hexes to follow have as subjects men who carry out daily activities (medieval iconographic tradition)
May (man in a field of flowers with a bunch of flowers in his hand), June (a male figure mowing the hay), July (reaper), August (midwife male body, coming out of the river while drinking), September picker), October (ornicoltore), November (man in the field with oxen), December (sower), January (man hunting followed by dogs).
Foliage on the walls there are three stucco medallions representing the fire elements (the cerbero and Vulcano), water (Neptune and the sea horses) and air (Juno and peacocks).