This picture depicts the cry of St. Peter, sorry for having denied three times denied Jesus Christ. The apostle is depicted weeping and praying, looking up to the sky, beside a large walled wall. On the left, however, it is a landscape landscape dominated by dense clouds, which even more emphasize Peter's mood, and from a circular plan, it is possible to refer to the Temple of Jerusalem or the Hadrian's mausoleum
The canvas is considered as an autographed copy or a paint shop of the paintings kept at the National Gallery in Edinburgh.