The neo-Renaissance monumental staircase was built between 1924 and 1930 by the architect Luigi Marangoni. The structure is entirely in Travertino di Tivoli and is supported by pillars with capitals depicting Italian victories against Austria through coats of arms, monuments and symbols of the cities recaptured from Italy in the territories known as the three Venezie (Friuli Venezia Giulia, Trentino and Dalmatia ).
To the right of the first ramp there is a fountain, no longer in operation, with three heads of crowned lions symbolizing Dalmatia, and a lower part of an inscription alongside the coat of arms of the kingdom of Italy on the left and that of the capital of Dalmatia, Zara, right.