This processional board is painted on both sides. On one side (recto) is depicted the Virgin that protects the faithful with an angel-guarded mantle. The faithful are divided by gender and social class. Among the first files are the "Flagellants", penitent members of the congregation who commissioned the table. To the left is also represented the ecclesiastical hierarchy guided by the pope.
Iconography refers to a plague epidemic, after which a thank-you procession would be organized.
On the other side of the table there is St. John the Baptist (Patriarch of Fabriano, probably the city represented in the background) and San Sebastiano, the protector of the plague.
The work is attributed to an artist of the workshop of Gentile De 'Fabriano, active in the town of Marcholo di Staffolo.
