The fountain was built in the years 1729-30 by Carlo Monaldi on behalf of the Venetian ambassador Borbon Morosini, who by building this structure solved the water supply problems of the Palace.
The opera represents "Venice who marries the sea" and celebrates the Republic. At the foot of the statue there is the lion of San Marco, while Venice stands in the head of the dog hat and holds a ring in his right hand protruding forward, symbol of the marriage with the sea. On the perimeter of the tub there are four putti that carry shields with above engraved the names of the greatest Venetian conquests.
